Finding Aid for William T. Gossett papers, 1927-1987
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
- Topical Files
  - William T. Gossett
    - Hughes, Charles Evan (lecture and article)
      - Drafts 1973-1974 (Box 11)
    - Institute of Judicial Administration 1968-1974 (Box 11)
    - International Bar Association 1970 (Box 11)
    - International Juvenile Justice Standards Project
      - Correspondence 1971-1979, 9 folders (Box 11)
      - Miscellaneous
        - Executive Committee Meeting November 18, 1977 (Box 11)
        - Presentation to ABA Endowment 1972-1974 (Box 11)
        - Printed material 1977, undated (Box 11)
    - International Legal Aid Association (Box 12)
    - Judicial Merit Selection Committee (Box 12)
    - Lawyers Committee for Civil Rights Under Law (Box 12)
    - Legal Aid and Defender Association of Detroit (Future Planning Committee) (Box 12)
    - Legal Services Program Correspondence 1973-1979, 3 folders (Box 12)
    - Meskill, Thomas (nomination) 1975 (Box 12)
    - McGill, William J. (campus government) 1970 (Box 12)
    - National Bar Association 1970 (Box 12)
    - National Conference of Judicial Councils 1969-1971 (Box 12)
    - National Legal Aid and Defender Association
      - Correspondence 1967-1979 (Box 12)
      - Annual Reports 1954-1968 (Box 12)
    - Powell, Louis F., Jr. 1971 (Box 12)
    - Office of Economic Opportunity (OEO), National Advisory Committee Correspondence 1969-1972, 2 folders (Box 12)
    - Scribes 1958-1975 (Box 12)
    - Senate Select Committee on Presidential Campaign Activities 1970-1974 (Box 12)
    - Sixth Circuit Court of Appeals 1973-1975 (Box 12)
    - Watergate 1973-1974 (Box 12)
    - Wiretapping Symposium 1973 (Box 12)
    - WWWW Citizen of the Day Award May 23, 1969 (Box 12)
    - 1979 Sixth Circuit Conference, Planning Committee (Box 12)
- Public Service Files
  The Public Service series includes files about many of the charitable organizations and activities which were of interest to Gossett, including the Detroit Council of Churches and the National Conference of Christians and Jews.
  - Charities and Activities
    - American Jewish Congress, Amity Award 1961-1968 (Box 13)
    - Association for American Achievement 1975 (Box 13)
    - Birmingham-Bloomfield Community Action Council 1971 (Box 13)
    - Civil Rights Commission (Michigan) 1967-1969 (Box 13)
    - Council for Financial Aid to Education 1971-1973 (Box 13)
    - Council for Public Interest Law (CPIL), Correspondence 1974-1978, 8 folders (Box 13)
    - Detroit Council of Churches 1952-1974
      - Correspondence 1960-1974, 3 folders (Box 13)
      - Advisory Committee on Financial Policy 1961 (Box 13)
      - Orders of Worship 1954-1962 (Box 13)
      - Layman of the Year Award 1960 (Box 13)
      - "What My Religion Means to Me, " clipping from Detroit Free Press, 1952 (Box 13)
    - Detroit Symphony Orchestra 1976-1979 (Box 13)
    - Economic Club of Detroit 1962-1979 (Box 13)
    - Gordin, Burton (Memorial Scholarship Foundation) 1972 (Box 13)
    - Hall of Fame for Great Americans 1969-1973 (Box 13)
    - Hart, Philip A. (Memorial Scholarship Committee) 1976-1977 (Box 13)
    - Helsinki Watch 1977-1978 (Box 13)
    - Theodore Levin Memorial Foundation 1972-1976 (Box 13)
    - Metropolitan Fund, Ad Hoc Legal Committee 1976 (Box 13)
    - National Committee on U.S.-China Relations 1972-1978 (Box 13)
    - National Conference of Christians and Jews 1970-1971 (Box 13)
    - National Committee for Commitment to Brotherhood 1970-April 1971, 2 folders (Box 13)
    - National Municipal League, Annual Conference 1979 (Box 13)
    - Project Start 1976-1978 (Box 13)
    - Public Utilities Shareholders Association 1977 (Box 13)
    - Reduction of Homicides Through Education, Inc. 1977 (Box 13)
    - Task Force on International Development 1969-1973 (Box 13)
    - University of Michigan President's Club 1978 (Box 13)
    - Young Americans for Responsible Action 1975-1978 (Box 13)
- Hospitals and Social Service Organizations
  The Hospitals and Social Service Organizations series concerns his work with Harper Hospital, New Detroit, inc., an the United Negro College Fund.
  - Harper Hospital
    - Correspondence 1966-1973, 2 folders (Box 14)
    - By-Laws 1966-1970 (Revisions) (Box 14)
    - Financial Statements 1975-1976 (Box 14)
    - Detroit Medical Center Cooperative 1970-1971 (Box 14)
    - Edward A. Krug Estate 1971 (Box 14)
    - Investment Authority 1970-1973 (Box 14)
    - Merger with Grace Hospital 1973 (Box 14)
  - United Hospitals 1974-1978
    - Correspondence 1974-1978 (Box 14)
    - Minutes 1975-1978, 2 folders (Box 14)
    - Printed Material (Annual Reports, By-Laws) 1973-1976 (Box 14)
  - New Detroit, Inc.
    - Correspondence 1970-1978, 3 folders (Box 14)
    - Combined Agency Narcotics Enforcement (CANE) Project 1974-1975 (Box 14)
    - Handguns 1975 (Box 14)
    - Heroin Problem 1977 (Box 14)
    - Referendum "E" 1972 (Box 14)
    - Printed Material 1968-1979, 2 folders (Box 14)
  - Professional Skills Alliance, Correspondence 1972, 1973 (Box 14)
  - United Negro College Fund
    - Correspondence
      - General 1967-1978, 3 folders (Box 14)
      - Michigan Campaign 1963-1980 (Box 14)
    - Printed Material, General 1974-1977, 3 folders (Box 14)
    - Minutes, Annual Meetings 1970-1977 (Box 14)
- Colleges, Universities, and Schools
  Gossett's relationships to Colleges, Universities, and Schools is documented through correspondence, minutes, and miscellanea. Most of the files relate to Atlanta University, Morehouse College, and Columbia University.
  - Atlanta University
    - Correspondence 1957-1978, 3 folders (Box 15)
    - Minutes (Board of Trustees) 1973-1979, 3 folders (Box 15)
    - Search Committee for New President 1977 (Box 15)
    - Financial Data 1976-1977 (Box 15)
  - Coe College Correspondence 1963-1979 (Box 15)
  - Columbia University
    - Correspondence
      - General 1968-1979, 3 folders (Box 15)
      - Miscellaneous 1968-1979 (Box 15)
    - Alumni and related activities
      - Alumni Fund Campaign 1973-1978 (Box 15)
      - Columbia Club of Michigan 1962-1979 (Box 15)
      - Columbia University Campaign 1965-1968, 2 folders (Box 15)
      - Frank Hogan Scholarship Fund 1970-1974 (Box 15)
      - House Counsel 1971-1974 (Box 15)
      - Pulitzer Prize Awards 1967-1972 (Box 15)
      - Registration (Board of Trustees) 1965-1974 (Box 15)
      - Rockefeller Center Lease 1969 (Box 15)
      - Harlan Fiske Stone Fellowship 1970-1978 (Box 15)
      - Strickman, Robert (cigarette filter) 1967 (Box 15)
  - Morehouse College
    - Correspondence 1960-1978 (Box 15)
    - Minutes, Board of Trustees 1976-1978 (Box 15)
    - National Fund 1972-1976 (Box 15)
    - Financial Data 1973-1976 (Box 15)
  - Spelman College Correspondence 1972-1973 (Box 15)
  - University of Utah National Advisory Council 1968-1972, 2 folders (Box 16)
  - Cranbrook Foundation
    - Correspondence 1960-1972, 2 folders (Box 16)
    - Honorary Director 1968 (Box 16)
    - Trust Instrument Undated (Box 16)
- Personal Correspondence 1947-1962
  Gossett's Personal Correspondence spans the years of 1947 to 1962, with an emphasis on the period of 1947 to 1955.
  - A-W, 26 folders (Box 16)
    (includes named folders for O'Meara, Joseph, WCHB and WCHD Award, Woolfenden, Henry L.
- Biographical and Personal
  The Biographical and Personal Materials series documents a variety of Gossett's activities. For example, in Gossett's interviews with the Ford Corporate History Project, he offers detailed interpretations of personal dynamics and strategy in Ford's resurgence under Henry Ford II. There are three subseries: Clippings (1930-1983), Personal Correspondence (1940-1987) and papers regarding Gossett's tenure as Deputy Special Representative (1962-1963). This series' individual files document milestones in Gossett's professional career, for example, Gossett's first job offer (from Charles Evans Hughes private practice) and his letter of resignation from Ford are in this series. The Clippings files are arranged chronologically and trace Gossett's personal and professional lives, including Ford's reorganization in the 1940s. These files are most complete from 1945 (Gossett's appointment as general counsel to Bendix Aviation) through the early 1960s.
  - Biographical Material (Box 16)
  - Clippings
    - 1918-1947 (scattered) (Box 16)
    - 1948-1964 (scattered) (Box 17)
    - 1965-1983 (scattered) (Box 18)
  - Correspondence
    - Miscellaneous
      - B-R 1940-1987 (Box 18)
      - S-Z 1943-1986 (Box 18)
    - Ferry, W.H. (Box 18)
    - Morrison, H. Graham (Box 18)
    - Surbeck, Homer (Box 18)
  - Deputy Special Representative
    - Appointment (Box 18)
    - Clippings (Box 18)
    - Resignation (Box 18)
  - Gossett, Elizabeth Evans Hughes (Box 18)
  - Interviews with David Lewis for Ford Corporate History Project 1987 (Box 18)
  - Resignation from Ford Motor Company 1962 (Box 18)
  - State Bar Admission and Employment (Box 18)
- Speeches, Articles, and Statements 1954-1978
  Unlike the 1981 Accession, Gossett's Speeches, Articles, and Statements are arranged in alphabetical order by the composition's name or topic. Some of these include correspondence about the composition's content.
  - "Bar Related Title Assuring Companies," 1965 (Box 18)
  - Ford Motor Company, Miscellaneous articles and speeches (Box 18)
  - Forward for Pound Conference book 1978 (Box 18)
  - Hughes, Charles H., articles about (Box 18)
  - Letters to the Editor re: Gag Rule 1971 (Box 18)
  - Miscellaneous Speeches (Box 18)
  - Miscellaneous Articles (Box 18)
  - Remarks to the New York Times re: Senator McCarthy, 1954 (Box 18)
  - Statement Before the House Judiciary Committee re: Constitutional Amendment for Direct Election of the President and Vice President 1969 (Box 18)
- Photographs
  The Photographs series includes photos of both Mr. and Mrs. Gossett; formal portraits (of Gossett) as well as posed shots to commemorate various events. This series also includes an album of photographs from Ford Motor Company's Waldorf Premiere of the 1949 Ford.
  - Ford Motor Company June 1948 Waldorf Premiere (Box 18)
  - Gossett, William T. (Box 18)
  - Gossett, Elizabeth Evans Hughes (Box 18)
- Twentieth Century-Fox
  - Reorganization of Wesco Corporation 1933-1936, 5 volumes (Box 19)
  - Reorganization of Fox Film Corporation and Twentieth Century Pictures, Inc. July-August 1935 (Box 19)